[Document(metadata={'producer': 'Adobe Acrobat Pro 11.0.16 Paper Capture Plug-in', 'creator': 'Smart Touch 1.7', 'creationdate': '2015-11-14T16:46:45+05:30', 'moddate': '2016-06-09T17:01:57+05:30', 'title': '1995.1.SCR.148', 'source': './Data/-0___jonew__judis__10988.pdf', 'total_pages': 15, 'page': 0, 'page_label': '1'}, page_content='A \nB \nDR. EsAL KRI SHNA AGARWAL \nv. \nSTATE OF UTTA R PRADESH AND ORS. \nJANUARY 10, 1995 \n[S.C. AGRAWA L AND FAIZAN UDDIN, JJ.] \nSe1vice law-{}ttar Pradesh State Un iversities Act, 197~Section 31-\nA-Personal Promotion Scheme-Length of service and qualifications \nprescribed by Notification dated 21-2-85-Prom otion to grade of Professor \nC could only be validly effected from 21-2-1985--Clause 18.05-lnter se seniority \nof teachers appointed by personal promotion and by direct recruitment\xad\nProf essor in Physics-Detennination of seniority according to length of con\xad\ntinuolts service in a substantive capacity in such cadre-Service of those \npromoted under Personal Promotion Scheme- To be counted from 21-02-85. \nD \nE \nF \nConstitution of India, 1950-Article 226-Writ-Availability of alterna\xad\ntive remedy-Party non-suited by High Co urt five years after admitting the writ \npetition-Held, not justified. \nTh e appellant and respondents Nos. 4 and 5 were employed as \nReaders in the Physics Department of the Allahabad University. In 1983 \napplications were invited for direct recruitment to one permanent post of \nProfessor. The appellant wa s appointed to the post substantively by an \norder dated No vember 9, 1984. On November 9, 1984, respondents Nos. 4 \nand 5 were prom oted in the grade of Professor under the Personal Promo\xad\ntion Scheme which wa s framed on December 12, 1983 and came into force \nby amendment to the Act on October 10, 1984. \nThe appellant after probation for one year was confirmed on the post \nof profrssor w.e.f. November 9, 1985~ The Seniorty Committee of the \nFaculty of Science considering the inter se seniority of the appellant and \nrespondents Nos. 4 and 5 came to the conclusion that the appointments \nG on cadre posts and personal promotions cases constituted two different \ncategories so as not to be intermingled and should be maintained separate\xad\nly and the teachers appointed on cadre P?sts by direct recruitment should \nbe treated senior to those teachers appointed under Personal Promotion \nScheme irrespective of their date of appointment. The Seniority Co mmittee \nH placed the appellant, who held the cadre post of Professor above respon-\n148'), Document(metadata={'producer': 'Adobe Acrobat Pro 11.0.16 Paper Capture Plug-in', 'creator': 'Smart Touch 1.7', 'creationdate': '2015-11-14T16:46:45+05:30', 'moddate': '2016-06-09T17:01:57+05:30', 'title': '1995.1.SCR.148', 'source': './Data/-0___jonew__judis__10988.pdf', 'total_pages': 15, 'page': 1, 'page_label': '2'}, page_content="DR.B.K.AGRAWALv. STATE 149 \ndents 4 and 5 who were promoted to the grade of Professor under the A \nPersonal Promotion Scheme. \nRespondents 4 and 5 submitted representations before the Executive \nCouncil against the said decision of the Seniority Committee. The Execu-\ntive Council altered the seniorty and placed respondents 4 and 5 above the \nappellant. Writ Petition filed by the appellant against the decision of the B \nExecutive Council was dismissed by the High Court on the ground that \nalternative remedy of reference to the Chancellor u/s 68 of the Uttar \nPradesh State Universities Act, 1973 was available to the appellant. \nThe High Court observed that there was controversy with regard to C \nnature of appointments since the appellant claimed that be had been \nappointed against a regular vacancy while the respondents asserted that \nall three had been granted personal promotion and that there was also a \ndispute regarding the date on which the appellant joined the post of \nProfessor. D \nThe appellant contended that the High Court was in error in dis\xad\nmissing the Writ Petition on the ground of availability of an alternative \nremedy having regard to the fact that the Writ Petition had been filed in \n1988 and it bad been admitted and was pending in the High Court for the \npast more than live years. Further, there was no dispute regarding the E \nappellant's selection by the Selection Committee for appointment to the \npermanent post of Professor, which recommendation bad been accepted \nby the Executive Council. Also, the appellant's inclusion in the list of \npersonal promotees did not mean that his appointment was by way of \npersonal permotion and not on the basis of selection for the cadre post F \nwhich was advertised. \nIt was submitted that since the appellant was appointed on the post \nof Professor on November 9, 1984, the seniority should be regulated by the \nprovisions contained in the Statutes of the University as they existed on \nthe said date and that the amendments which were made in the Statutes G \nby notification dated February 21, 1985 would have no application in the \nmatter of determination of the appellant's seniority. Under clause (b) of \nStatute 18.05, as it stood on November 9, 1984, when the appellant joined \nas Professor, be, holding the selection post of Professor in Physics Faculty, \nwas senior to respondents Nos. 4 and 5 who were promotees under the H"), Document(metadata={'producer': 'Adobe Acrobat Pro 11.0.16 Paper Capture Plug-in', 'creator': 'Smart Touch 1.7', 'creationdate': '2015-11-14T16:46:45+05:30', 'moddate': '2016-06-09T17:01:57+05:30', 'title': '1995.1.SCR.148', 'source': './Data/-0___jonew__judis__10988.pdf', 'total_pages': 15, 'page': 2, 'page_label': '3'}, page_content='150 SUPREME COURT REPORTS (1995] 1 S.C.R. \nA Personal Promotion Scheme. It was urged that although Section 31-A, \nwhich provided for personal promotion was introduced in the Act w.e.f. \nOctober 10, 1984, it could be given effect to only after the length of service \nas well as the qualifications were prescribed in the Statutes and this was \ndone only by the amendments introduced by notification dated February \nB 21, 1985. Therefore, it was contended that personal promotion of respon\xad\ndents Nos. 4 and 5 could have legal effect only from the date of such \namendment in the Statutes and they should be treated to have been \npromoted w.e.f. February 21, 1985. It was argued that since the appellant \njoined as Professor on November 9, 1984, he should be treated as senior \nto respondents Nos. 4 and 5. \nc \nThe respondents urged that since the validity of appointment of \nrespondents Nos. 4 and 5 w.e.f. November 9, 1984 had not been assailed \nby the appellant, he should not be permitted to raise this question at this \nstage. Also, since the seniority of the appellant and respondents Nos. 4 and \nD 5 was determined by the Executive Council after the Statutes had been \namended by notification dated February 21, 1985 the criterion for rixing \nthe seniority would be that laid down in the Statutes on the date when such \ndetermination was made and that the seniority was properly determined \nin accordance with the provisions of the Statutes 18.05 as amended by \nNotification dated February 21, 1985. It was further contended that since \nE the appellant and respondents 4 and 5 joined as professors on the same \ndate, their inter se seniority should be determined by the length of their \nservice as Readers and on that basis the respondents would rank senior \nas they bad longer length of service as Readers than the appellant. \np Allowing the appeal, !bis Court \nHEW : 1. The High Court was not right in dismissing the Writ \nPetition on the ground of availability of an alternative remedy u/s 68 of the \nUttar Pradesh State Universities Act, 1973, especially when the Writ \nPetition that"was filed in 1988 had already been admitted and was pending \nG in the High Conrt for the past more than five years. Since the question \nthat was raised involved a pure qnestion of law and even if the matter was \nreferred to the Chancellor u/s 68 of the Act ii was bound to be agitated in \nthe court by the party aggrieved by the order of the Chancellor, this was \nnot case where the High Court should have non-suited the appellant on \nH the ground of availability of an alternative remedy. (156-G-H, 157-A]'), Document(metadata={'producer': 'Adobe Acrobat Pro 11.0.16 Paper Capture Plug-in', 'creator': 'Smart Touch 1.7', 'creationdate': '2015-11-14T16:46:45+05:30', 'moddate': '2016-06-09T17:01:57+05:30', 'title': '1995.1.SCR.148', 'source': './Data/-0___jonew__judis__10988.pdf', 'total_pages': 15, 'page': 3, 'page_label': '4'}, page_content='DR. B.K. AGRAWAL v. STATE 151 \n2.1. In view of the provisions contained in Sections 31-A and 2(1) of A \nthe Act there is no escape from the conclusion that respondents Nos. 4 and \n5 could not be given promotion under the Personal Promotion Scheme till \nthe necessary provisions prescribing the length of service and qualifica\xad\ntions for such promotion were made in the Statutes of the University and \nsince this was done by Notification dated February 21, 1985, promotion B \nunder the Personal Promotion Scheme could not be made prior to February \n21, 1985. [160-H, 161-Al \n2.2. The Executive Council in its Resolution No. 198 dated November \n8, 1984 had accepted tlie recommendations of the Selection Committee for \npromotion of respondents Nos. 4 and 5 on the basis of Government Orders C \ndated December 12, 1983 and February 25, 1984. At that time Section 31 of \nthe Act provided for appointment of teachers by direct recruitment and did \nnot envisage promotion from a lower leaching post to a higher teaching \npost. The orders of the Government aforementioned could not be given \nelTect till necessary amendment was maile in the Act making provision for D \npersonal promotion. This was done by introducing Section 31-A by U.P. Act \nNo. 9 of 1985 with elTect from October 10, 1984. But Section 31-A could be \ngiven effect only after the necessary provision was made in the Statutes \nprescribing the length of service and the qualiftcations for personal promo\xad\ntion. This was done by the notification dated February 21, 1985. The promo-\ntion of respondents Nos. 4 and 5 to the grade of Professor under the E \nPersonal Promotion Scheme could, therefore, not be made prior to \nFebruary 21, 1985 and it bad to be treated to have been made with elTect \nfrom February 21, 1985. The inter se seniority of the appellant and respon╖ \ndents Nos. 4 and 5 bad to be determined on that basis. [161-B-D] \n2.3. Under the Statutes as amended by notification dated February \n21, 1985, it is laid down in clause (b) of Statute 18.05 thatin the same cadre, \ninter se seniority of teachers, appointed by personal promotion or by direct \nrecruitment, shall be determined according to length of continuous service \nF \nin a substantive capacity in such cadre. Since the promotion of respondents G \nNos. 4 and 5 can be treated to be valid only with elTect from February 21, \n1985 their service in the cadre of Professor had to be counted from \nFebruary 21, 1985 while the service of the appellant had to be counted from \nNovember 9, 1984. The appellant was, therefore, entitled to be placed above \nrespondents Nos. 4 and 5 in so far as seniority in the cadre of Professor \nwas concerned. (161-G-H, 162-A) H'), Document(metadata={'producer': 'Adobe Acrobat Pro 11.0.16 Paper Capture Plug-in', 'creator': 'Smart Touch 1.7', 'creationdate': '2015-11-14T16:46:45+05:30', 'moddate': '2016-06-09T17:01:57+05:30', 'title': '1995.1.SCR.148', 'source': './Data/-0___jonew__judis__10988.pdf', 'total_pages': 15, 'page': 4, 'page_label': '5'}, page_content="152 SUPREME COURT REPORTS (1995] 1 S.C.R. \nA CIVIL APPELLATE JURISDICTION : Civil Appeal No. 607 of \n1995. \nFrom the Judgment and Order dated 6.1.94 of the Allahabad High \nCourt in C.M.P.W.P. No. 15566 of 1988. ' \nB M.L. Bhat, Arun Jaitley, S.B. Sanyal, Ms. Purnima Bhat, Sunil Gupta, \nSunil Kr. Singh, U.N. Singh, R.K. Sharma, Ms. Vijaya Lakshmi Menon, \nManinder Singh and K.L. Taneja for the appearing parties. \nThe Judgment of the Court was delivered by \nC S.C. AGRAWAL, J. Leave granted. \nWe have heard learned counsel for the parties. \nThis appeal involves the question regarding inter se seniority of the \nappellant-Dr. Bal Krishna Agarwal and respondents Nos. 4 and 5, Dr. \nD Murli Manohar Joshi, and Dr. P.K. Sharma as Professors in Physics in the \nAllahabad University (hereinafter referred to as 'the University'). The \nExecutive Council of the University by resolution dated July 16, 1978, \ndeclared respondents Nos. 4 and 5 as senior to the appellant. Writ Petition \nNo. 15566 of 1988 filed by the appellant against the said resolution of the \nE Executive Council was diòmissed by the Allahabad High Court by judgment \ndated January 6, 1994 on the ground that alternative remedy of reference \nto the Chancellor under Section 68 of the Uttar Pradesh State Universities \nAct, 1973 (hereinafter r~ferred to as 'the Act') was available to the appel\xad\nlant. \nF Section 31 of the Act provides for appointment of teachers. In \nsub-section (10) of Section 31 it is prescribed that no selection for any \nappointment shall be made except after advertisement of the vacancy in at \nleast three issues of two newspapers having adequate circulation in Uttar \nPradesh. In view of the said provision appointment of teachers in the \nUniversity could only be made by direct recruitment by inviting applica-\nG tions and promotion from a lower teaching post to a higher teaching post \nwas not envisaged. This led to stagnation and consequent frustration among \nthe teachers in the various Universities governed by the Act. In order to \nremove this grievence the Government of Uttar Pradesh, by order dated \nDecember U, 1983, framed a Personal Promotion Scheme whereunder \nH personal promotion was to be given to a teacher on the basis of continuo~"), Document(metadata={'producer': 'Adobe Acrobat Pro 11.0.16 Paper Capture Plug-in', 'creator': 'Smart Touch 1.7', 'creationdate': '2015-11-14T16:46:45+05:30', 'moddate': '2016-06-09T17:01:57+05:30', 'title': '1995.1.SCR.148', 'source': './Data/-0___jonew__judis__10988.pdf', 'total_pages': 15, 'page': 5, 'page_label': '6'}, page_content='DR.B.K.AGRAWALv. STATE[AGRAWAL,J.] 153 \nservice rendered in the department for a certain period. By order dated A \nFreburary 25, 1984 the said order dated December 12, 1983 was modified \nand it was decided to grant personal promotion to the post of Reader to \nall those full time and regularly appointed lecturers on the Government \napproved posts of Universities governed and administered by the Act who \npossess Ph.D degrees and have completed 13 years approved, full time B \nregular and continuous service and those who are not Ph.D after 16 years \napproved, full time and regular and continuous service. It was also decided \nto grant personal promotion to the post of Professor to Readers after 10 \nyears continuous and regular service as Reader from the date of taking \nover charge after issue of the said order. In the said order it was stated \nthat the personal promotion would be granted to teachers subject to the C \nrestrictions set but in sub-paragraphs (1) to (12) of paragraph 1 in the said \norder. In sub-paragraph (12) it was stated tpat the seniority of the Teachers \nwould be regulated as per Regulations of die concerned University. By the \nsaid letter the Vice-Chancellors of all the State Universities were directed \nto send the draft regulation for carrying out necessary amendment in the D \nRegulations of the concerned University to the Education Department for \napproval. In order to give effect to the policy contained in the aforesaid \norders of the Government of Uttar Pradesh, Section 31-A was inserted in \nthe Act by U.P. Act No. 9 of 1985 which came into force on October 10, \n1984. Section 31-A provides as under:-\nE \n"31-A. Personal promotion to teachers of University. \n(1) Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any \nother provision of this Act, a Lecturer or Reader in the University \nsubstantively appointed under Section 31, who has put in such \nlength of service and possesses such qualifications, as may be F \nprescribed, may be given personal promotion, respectively to the \npost of Reader or Professor. \n(2) Such personal promotion shall be given on the recommendation \nof the Selection Committee, constituted under clause (a) of sub- G \nsection ( 4) of Section 31, in such manner and subject to such \nconditions as may be prescribed. \n(3) Nothing contained in this section shall affect the posts of the \nteachers of the University to be filled by direct appointment in \naccordance with the provisions of Section 31." H'), Document(metadata={'producer': 'Adobe Acrobat Pro 11.0.16 Paper Capture Plug-in', 'creator': 'Smart Touch 1.7', 'creationdate': '2015-11-14T16:46:45+05:30', 'moddate': '2016-06-09T17:01:57+05:30', 'title': '1995.1.SCR.148', 'source': './Data/-0___jonew__judis__10988.pdf', 'total_pages': 15, 'page': 6, 'page_label': '7'}, page_content="154 SUPREME COURT REPORTS (1995] 1 S.C.R. \nA In view of sub-section (1) of Section 31-A personal promotion as_ \nenvisaged by Section 31-A could be given only after the length of service \nand the qualifications were prescribed. The word 'prescribed' is defined in \nSection 2(14) of the Act to mean prescribed by the Statutes. T~e necessary \namendment to give effect to the scheme of personal promotion as en-\nB visaged by Section 31-A of the Act was made in the Statutes of the \nUniversity by notification dated February 21, 1985 whereby Statute 11.12-B \nwas introduced and the categories of teachers of the University who would \nbe eligible for the personal promotion to the post of Readers and Profes\xad\nsors and the mode of such promotion were prescribed. \nC The appellant and respondents Nos. 4 and 5 were employed as \nReaders in the Physics Department of the University. In October 1983 an \nadvertisement was published inviting applications for direct recruitment on \none permanent post of Professor in the Physics Department of the Univer\xad\nsity. In response to the said advertisement applications were submitted by \nD the appellant and respondents Nos. 4 and 5 alongwith other aeplicants. \nThe said applications were considered by the Selection Committee under \nthe Faculty of Science and the Selection Committee, in its report dated \nJuly 22, 1984, recommended a panel containing the names of the appellant \nand respondents Nos. 4 and 5 for appointment on the post of Professor in \nPhysics. The name of the appellant was placed at the top in the said panel. \nE The Selection Committee also considered the appellant and respondents \nNos. 4 and 5 for promotion to the grade of Professor under the Personal \nPromotion Scheme and in its report dated July 22, 1984 the Selection \nCommittee recommended all three of them for such promotion. The said \nrecommendations of the Selection Committee were considered by the \np Executive Council of the University at the meeting held on November 8, \n1984. By Resolution No. 197 the Executive Council accepted the recom\xad\nmendations of the Selection Committee and recorded that the appellant be \nappointed as Professor in Physics substantively. By Resolution No. 198 the \nExecutive Council accepted the recommendations of the Selection Com\xad\nmittee under the Personal Promotion Scheme and recorded that the ap-\nG pellant and respondents Nos. 4 and 5 be promoted to the grade of \nProfessor in terms of Government Orders dated December 12, 1983 and \nFebruary 25, 1984. In the said Resolution the names of the appellant and \nthe respondents Nos. 4 and 5 were shown in the following order :-\nH 1. Dr. Bal Krishana Agrawal (appellant)"), Document(metadata={'producer': 'Adobe Acrobat Pro 11.0.16 Paper Capture Plug-in', 'creator': 'Smart Touch 1.7', 'creationdate': '2015-11-14T16:46:45+05:30', 'moddate': '2016-06-09T17:01:57+05:30', 'title': '1995.1.SCR.148', 'source': './Data/-0___jonew__judis__10988.pdf', 'total_pages': 15, 'page': 7, 'page_label': '8'}, page_content='DR. B.K.AGRAWAL v. STATE [AGRAWAL,J.] 155 \n2. Dr. M.M. Joshi (respondent No. 4) A \n3. Dr. P.K. Sharma (respondent No. 5) \nOn the basis of the said resolutions, by order dated November 9, \n1984, the appellant was appointed on the post of Professor in Physics. B \nRespondents Nos. 4 and 5 were promoted in the grade of Professor under \nthe Personal Promotion Scheme on November 9, 1984. The appointment \nof the appellant on the post of Professor was on probation for one year \nand he was confirmed on the said post of Professor with effect from \nNovember 9, 1985. The matter of inter se seniority of the appellant and \nrespondents Nos. 4 and 5 was considered by the Seniority Committee of C \nthe Faculty of Science in its meeting held on December 22, 1986 and \nJanuary 4, 1987. The Committee came to the conclusion that the appoint\xad\nments on cadre posts and personal promotion cases constitute two dif\xad\nferent categories and could not be intermingled for the purpose of \ndetermination of seniority and that the seniority of teachers in the cadre D \nposts should be maintained separately from that of the personal promotees \nand that the teachers appointed on cadre posts by direct recruitment \nshould be treated senior to those teachers appointed under Personal \nPromotion Scheme irrespective of their date of appointment. The Seniority \nCommittee decided to place the appellant, who was holding the cadre post \nof Professor, above respondents Nos. 4 and 5 who were promoted to the E \ngrade of Professor under the Personal Promotion Scheme. Feeling ag\xad\ngrieved by the said decision of the Seniority Committee respondents Nos. \n4 and 5 submitted representations which were considered by the Executive \nCouncil in its meeting held on July 16, 1988. The Executive Council altered \nthe seniority as fixed by the Seniority Committee and placed respondents F \nNos. 4 and 5 above the appellant. The said decision of the Executive \nCouncil was assailed by the appellant by filing the Writ Petition giving rise \nto this appeal. \nThe High Court has observed that there was controversy in regard \nto every question of fact in as much as there was dispute with regard to G \nnature of appointments since the appellant claimed that he had been \nappointed against a regular vacancy which was assailed by the respondents \nwho asserted. that all three had been granted personal promotion and that \nthere was also a dispute regarding the date on which the appellant joined \nthe post of Professor. The High Court was of the view that the question as H'), Document(metadata={'producer': 'Adobe Acrobat Pro 11.0.16 Paper Capture Plug-in', 'creator': 'Smart Touch 1.7', 'creationdate': '2015-11-14T16:46:45+05:30', 'moddate': '2016-06-09T17:01:57+05:30', 'title': '1995.1.SCR.148', 'source': './Data/-0___jonew__judis__10988.pdf', 'total_pages': 15, 'page': 8, 'page_label': '9'}, page_content="156 SUPREME COURT REPORTS (1995) 1 S.C.R. \nA to whether the impugned order had been passed without affording an \noppertunity of hearing to the appellant was a question which can be \nappropriately decided only after investigation in the disputed questions of \nfact and that this was not a fit case in which the appellant should be allowed \nto by-pass the alternative remedy of reference to the Chancellor provided \nB under Section 68 of the Act. The High Court, therefore, dismissed the Writ \nPetition on the ground of availability of the alternative remedy and directed \nthat if the representation of the appellant under Section 68 of the Act was \nfiled within a period of two weeks, the bar of limitation would not be \napplied against the same and it should be decided on merits. \nC The learned counsel for the appellant has urged that the High Court \nwas in error in dismissing the Writ Petition of the appellant on the ground \nof availability of an alternative remedy having regard to the fact that the \nWrit Petition had been filed in 1988 and it had been admitted and was \npending in the High Court for the past more than five years. The learned \nD counsel has also urged that the High Court was not right in saying that \nthere was dispute on questions of fact. According to the learned counsel \nthere is no dispute that the appellant had been selected by the Selection \nCommittee for appointment on the permanent post of Professor which was \nadvertised and the said recommendation of the Selection Committee was \naccepted by the Executive Council in its Resolution No. 197 dated Novem-\nE ber 8, 1984. The fact that the name of the appellant was also included in \nthe list of Readers for personal promotion to the grade of Professor in \nResolution No. 198 of the Executive Council would not mean that the \nappointment of the appellant to the post of Professor was by way of \npersonal promotion and not on the basis of selection for the cadre post of \nF \nG \nProfessor which was advertised. The learned counsel also submitted that it \nis not the case of the appellant that he joined the post of Professor in \nPhysics oti November 8, 1984 and that his case is that the appellant as well \nas respondents Nos. 4 and 5 all joined 'as Professors in Physics on Novem\xad\nber 9, 1984. \nHaving regard to the aforesaid facts and circumstances, we are of \nthe view that the High Court was not right in dismissing the Writ Petition \nof the appellant on the ground of availability of an alternative. remedy \nunder Section 68 of the Act especially when the Writ Petition that was filed \nin 1988 had already been admitted and was pending in the High Court for \nH the past more than five years. Since the question that is raised involves a"), Document(metadata={'producer': 'Adobe Acrobat Pro 11.0.16 Paper Capture Plug-in', 'creator': 'Smart Touch 1.7', 'creationdate': '2015-11-14T16:46:45+05:30', 'moddate': '2016-06-09T17:01:57+05:30', 'title': '1995.1.SCR.148', 'source': './Data/-0___jonew__judis__10988.pdf', 'total_pages': 15, 'page': 9, 'page_label': '10'}, page_content='DR. B.K.AGRAWALv. STATE(AGRAWAL,J.] 157 \npure question of law and even if the matter is referred to the Chancellor A \nunder Section 68 of the Act it is bound to be agitated in the court by the \nparty aggtieved by the order of the Chancellor, we are of the view that this \nwas not a case where the Hi~ Court should have non-suited the appellant \non the ground of availability of an alternative remedy. We, therefore, \npropose to go into the merits of the question regarding inter se seniority of B \nthe appellant and respondents Nos. 4 and 5. We may, in this context, \nmention that the respondent No. 4 has already retired in January, 1994. \nProvisions with regard to seniority of teachers of University are \ncontained in Chapter 18 of the First Statutes of the University. Prior to the \namendments made by Notification dated February 21, 1985 the Statutes C \n. having bearing on the seniority of teachers of the University were as \nunder:-\n"18.05. The following rules shall be .followed in determining the \nseniority of teachers of the University :-\n(a) A Professor shall be deemed senior to every Reader, and \na Reader shall be deemed senior to every Lecturer. \n(b) In the same cadre, seniority of a teacher shall be determined \naccording to the length of his continnous service in a substantive \ncapacity in such cadre : \nProvided that where more than one al_lPointment to posts in a \ncadre have been made at the same tiine, and an order of preference \nor merii was indicated by the Selection Committee or by the \nExecuti~e Council, as the case may be, the seniority of the persons \nso appointed shall be governed by the order so indicated. \n( c) When any teacher holding substantive post in any University \n(other than the University of Allahabad) or in any constituent \ncollege or in any Institute whether in the State of Uttar Pradesh \nD \nE \nF \nor outside Uttar Pradesh is appointed whether before or after G \nAugust 1, 1981, to a post of corresponding rank or grade in the╖ \nUniversity, the period of service rendered by such teacher in that \ngrade or rank in such University shall be added to his length of \nservice. \n( d) When any teacher holding substantive post in any .college H'), Document(metadata={'producer': 'Adobe Acrobat Pro 11.0.16 Paper Capture Plug-in', 'creator': 'Smart Touch 1.7', 'creationdate': '2015-11-14T16:46:45+05:30', 'moddate': '2016-06-09T17:01:57+05:30', 'title': '1995.1.SCR.148', 'source': './Data/-0___jonew__judis__10988.pdf', 'total_pages': 15, 'page': 10, 'page_label': '11'}, page_content='158 SUPREME COURT REPORTS [1995] 1 S.C.R. \nA affiliated to or associated with any University is appointed whether \nbefore or after the commencement of these Statutes as a Lecturer \nin the University, then one half of the period of substantive service \nrendered by such teacher in such college shall be added to his \nlength of service. \nB \nc \nD \n( e) Service against an administrative appointment in any \nUniversity or institution shall not count for the purposes of \nseniority. \nExplanation :-In this Chapter, the expression "administrative ap\xad\npointment\' means an appointment made under sub-section ( 6) of \nSection 13. \n(f) Continuous service in a temporary post to which a teacher \nis appointed after reference to a Selection Committee, if followed \nby his appointment in a substantive capacity to that post under \nSection 31(3)(b) shall count towards seniority. \n18.06. Where more than one teacher are entitled to count the same \nlength of continuous service in the cadre to which they belong, the \nrelative seniority of such teachers shall be determined as below :-\nE (i) in the case of Professors, the length of substantive service \nas Reader shall be taken into consideration; \n(ii) in the case of Readers, the length of substantive service as \nLecturer shall be taken into consideration; \nF (iii) in the case of Professors, whose length of service aS \nG \nH \nReaders is also identical, the length of service as lecturer shall be \ntaken into consideration. \n18.07. Where more than one teacher are entitled to count the same \nlength of continuous service and their relative seniority cannot be \ndetermined in accordance with any of the foregoing provisions, \nthen the seniority of such teachers shall be determined on the basis \nof seniority in age. \n18.08. (1) Notwithstanding anything contained in any other Statute, \nif the Executive Council -'), Document(metadata={'producer': 'Adobe Acrobat Pro 11.0.16 Paper Capture Plug-in', 'creator': 'Smart Touch 1.7', 'creationdate': '2015-11-14T16:46:45+05:30', 'moddate': '2016-06-09T17:01:57+05:30', 'title': '1995.1.SCR.148', 'source': './Data/-0___jonew__judis__10988.pdf', 'total_pages': 15, 'page': 11, 'page_label': '12'}, page_content='DR. B.K.AGRAWAL v. STATE IAGRAWAL,J.] 159 \n(a) agrees with the recommendation of the Selection Commit- A \nte\'f, and approves two or more persons for appointment as teachers \nin the same Department, it shall, while recording such approval, \ndetermine the order of merit of such teachers; \n(b) does not agree with the recommendations of the Selection \nCommittee and refers the matter to the Chancellor under Section B \n31(8)( a), the Chancellor shall, in cases where appointment of two \nor more teachers in the same Department is involved, determine \nthe order of merit of such teachers at the time of deciding such \nreference; \n(2) The order of merit in which two or more teachers are placed C \nunder clause (1), shall be communicated to the teachers concerned \nbefore their appointment. \nBy virture of the amendments that have been introduced in the Statutes by \nNotification dated February 21, 1985, clause (b) of Statute 18.05 was D \nsubstituted as under :-\n"(b) In the same cadre, inter se seniority of teachers, appointed \nby personal promotion or by direct recruitment, shall be deter\xad\nmined according to length of continuous service in a substantive \ncapacity in such cadre : \nProvided that where more than one appointment have been \nmade by direct recruitment at the same time and an order of \npreference or merit was indicated by the Selection Committee or \nby the Execntive Council, as the case may be the inter se seniority \nof persons so appointed shall be governed by the order so indi\xad\ncated: \nProvided further that where more than one appointments have \nbeen made by promotion at the same time, the inter se seniority of \nE \nF \nthe teachers so appointed shall be the same as it was in the post G \nheld by them at the time of promotion." \nThe learned counsel for the appellant has submitted that since the \nappellant was appointed on the post of Professor in Physics on November \n9, 1984, the seniority should be regulated by the provisions contained in \nthe Statutes aS ihey existed on the said date and that the amendments H'), Document(metadata={'producer': 'Adobe Acrobat Pro 11.0.16 Paper Capture Plug-in', 'creator': 'Smart Touch 1.7', 'creationdate': '2015-11-14T16:46:45+05:30', 'moddate': '2016-06-09T17:01:57+05:30', 'title': '1995.1.SCR.148', 'source': './Data/-0___jonew__judis__10988.pdf', 'total_pages': 15, 'page': 12, 'page_label': '13'}, page_content='160 SUPREME COURT REPORTS . (1995] 1 S.C.R. \nA which were made in the Stat╡tes by notification dated February 21, 1985 \nwould have no application in the matter of determination of his seniority. \nUnder clause (b) of Statute 18.05, as it stood on.November 9, 1984, when \nthe appellant joined as Professor in Physics, appellant, who was holding \nthe selection post of Professor in Physics Faculty, was senior to respon-\nB dents Nos. 4 and 5 who were promotees under the Personal Promotion \nScheme. In this connection, the learned counsel has urged that although \nSection 31-A, which provides for personal promotion, was introduced in \nthe Act with effect from October 10, 1984 but the said provision could be \ngiven effect to only after the length of service as well as the qualifications \nwere prescribed in the Statutes and that this was done only by the amend-\nC ments that were introduced in the Statutes by notification dated February \n21, 1985 and, therefore, personal promotion of respondents Nos. 4 and 5 \ncould have legal effect only from the date of such amendment in the \nStatutes and that respondents Nos. 4 and 5 should be treated to have been \npromoted under Personal Promotion Scheme on the grade of Professor in \nD Physics with effect from February 21, 1985. Since the appellant joined as \nProfessor in Physics on November 9, 1984, he should be treated as senior \nto respondents Nos. 4 and 5. \nShri Sanyal, the learned senior counsel appearing for respondent No. \n5, however, urged that since the validity of appointment of respondents \nE Nos. 4 and 5 with effect from November 9, 1984 has not been assailed by \nthe appellant, he should not be permitted to raise this question at this stage. \nIt is no doubt true that the validity of the promotion of respondents Nos. \n4 and 5 has not been assailed by the appellant but all that he is pointing \nout is that in view of the provisions contained in Section 31-A of the Act \nF the promotion of respondents Nos. 4 and 5 under the Personal Promotion \nScheme could be made only after the length of service and qualifications \nwere prescribed by the Statutes and provisions in this regard were made \nin the Statutes only on February 21, 1985. In other words, what the \nappellant is saying is that the promotion of respondents Nos. 4 and 5 to \nthe grade of Professor can be regarded to have been made legally only with \nG effect from February 21, 1985. This does not involve a challenge to the \nvalidity of their promotion but only raises the question about the date from \nwhich it can be given effect to in law. We are of the opinion that in view \nof the provisions contained in Section 31-A and Section 2(14) of the Act \nthere is no escape from the conclusion that respondents N:os. 4 and s collld \nH not be given promotion under the Personal Promotion Scheme till the'), Document(metadata={'producer': 'Adobe Acrobat Pro 11.0.16 Paper Capture Plug-in', 'creator': 'Smart Touch 1.7', 'creationdate': '2015-11-14T16:46:45+05:30', 'moddate': '2016-06-09T17:01:57+05:30', 'title': '1995.1.SCR.148', 'source': './Data/-0___jonew__judis__10988.pdf', 'total_pages': 15, 'page': 13, 'page_label': '14'}, page_content='DR. B.K.AGRAWALv. STATE[AGRAWAL,J.j 161 \nnecessary provisions prescribing the length of service and the qualifications A \nfor such promotion were made in the Statutes and since this was done by \nNotification dated February 21, 1985, promotion under the Personal \nPromotion Scheme could not be made prior to February 21, 1985. The \nExecutive Council in its Resolution No. 198 dated November 8, 1984 had \naccepted the recommendations of the Selection Committee for promotion \nB of respondents Nos. 4 and 5 on the basis of Govermnent Orders dated \nDecember 12, 1983 and February 25, 1984. At that time Section 31 of the \nAct provided for appointment of teachers by direct recruitment and did \nnot envisage promotion from a lower teaching post to a higher teaching \npost. The orders of the Govermnent aforementioned could not be given \neffect till necessary amendment was made in the Act making provision for C \npersonal promotion. This was done by introducing Section 31-A by U.P. \nAct No. 9 of 1985 with effect from October 10, 1984. But Section 31-A \ncould be given effect only after the necessary provision was made in the \nStatutes prescribing the length of service and the qualifications for personal \npromotion. This was done by the notification dated February 21, 1985. The D \npromotion of respondents Nos. 4 and 5 to the grade of Professor under \nthe Personal Promotion Scheme could, therefore, not be made prior to \nFebruary 21, 1985 and it has to be treated to have been made with effect \nfrom February 21, 1985. Tbe inter se seniority of the appellant and respon\xad\ndents Nos. 4 and 5 has to be determined on that basis. \nShri Sanyal has also contended that since the seniority of the appel-\nE \nlant and respondents Nos. 4 and 5 was determined by the Executive \nCouncil after the Statutes had been amended by notification dated \nFebruary 21, 1985 the criterion for fixing the seniority would be that laid \ndown in the Statutes on the date when such determination was made and F \nthat the seniority was properly determined in accordance with the \nprovisions of the Statutes 18.05 as amended by Notification dated February \n21, 1985. We are unable to agree. Even under the Statutes as amended by \nnotification dated February 21, 1985 it is laid down in clause (b) of Statute \n18.05 that in the same cadre, inter se seniority of teachers, appointed by \npersonal promotion or by direct recruitment, shall be determined accord- G \ning to length of continuous service in a substantive capacity in such cadre. \nSince the promotion of respondents Nos. 4 and 5 can be treated to be valid \nonly with effect from February 21, 1985 their service in the cadre of \nProfessor has to be counted from February 21, 1985 while the service of \nthe appellant has to be counted from November 9, 1984. The appellant is, H'), Document(metadata={'producer': 'Adobe Acrobat Pro 11.0.16 Paper Capture Plug-in', 'creator': 'Smart Touch 1.7', 'creationdate': '2015-11-14T16:46:45+05:30', 'moddate': '2016-06-09T17:01:57+05:30', 'title': '1995.1.SCR.148', 'source': './Data/-0___jonew__judis__10988.pdf', 'total_pages': 15, 'page': 14, 'page_label': '15'}, page_content='162 SUPREME COURT REPORTS [1995] 1 S.C.R. \nA therefore, entitled to be placed above respondents Nos. 4 and 5 in so far \nas seniority in the cadre of Professor is concerned. \nShri Arun Jaitley, the learned counsel appearing for respondent No. \n4, has invited our attention to Statute 18.06 and has submitted that since \nthe appellant and respondents Nos. 4 and 5 joined as Professors on the \nB same date and have the same length of continuous service in the cadre of \nProfessor, their inter se seniority should be determined by virtue of the \nlength of their servicCas Readers and on that basis respondents Nos. 4 and \n5 would rank senior to the appellant since they had longer length of service \nas Readers than the appellant. This contention also proceeds on the basis \nC that the respondents Nos. 4 and 5 were validly promoted to the grade of \nProfessor on November 9, 1984 and the said contention would have no \nvalidity if it is held that promotion of respondents Nos. 4 and 5 to the grade \nof Professor under the Personal Promotion Scheme could only be legally \neffected from February 21, 1985. \nD For the reasons aforementioned, it must be held that the appellant \nshould have been treated as senior to respondents Nos. 4 and 5 in the cadre \nof Professor in Physics and the Executive Council was not justified in \nplacing him junior to the said respondents. The appeal is, therefore, \nallowed, the judgment of the High Court dated January 6, 1994 is set aside \nE and the Writ Petition filed by the appellant is allowed and it is directed \nthat the appellant should be treated as senior to respondents Nos. 4 and 5 \nas Professor in the Physics Department of the University. There is no order \nas to costs. \nAG. Appeal allowed.')]
